A Guide to the John Walter Wayland Papers, 1798-1950
Stewart Bell Jr. Archives, Handley Regional Library
Stewart Bell Jr. Archives, Handley Regional Library
John Walter Wayland Papers, 1890-1950
Stewart Bell Jr. Archives, Handley Regional Library
26 WFCHS
6.19 linear feet.
Wayland, John Walter
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to all researchers.
Acquisition Information
Acquired as a gift.
Alternative Form Available
Selected materials from this collection have been digitized and are available online through the Stewart Bell Jr. Digital Archives See the container list below for details and links to online content.
Biographical Information
Dr. John Walter Wayland was born on December 8, 1872 to John Wesley and Anna Kagey Wayland in Shenandoah County, Virginia. From 1890 to 1893, he taught in the public schools. He received a B.S. degree from Bridgewater College in Virginia and a Ph.D. in history from the University of Virginia in 1907. Wayland taught at several institutions in Virginia, including the University of Virginia and Madison College (now known as James Madison University), until his retirement in 1931. Following retirement he did extensive research and writing on the history, places and people of the Shenandoah Valley. During his life he authored 40 books and is one of the leading historians of the Shenandoah Valley of Virginia. Wayland died in 1962.
Scope and Content
The John Walter Wayland Papers contains a variety of materials written by Wayland, to include extensive correspondence, compilations of tombstone inscriptions, family Bible records, genealogies, military rosters, court records, and property books. The collection also includes some diaries from the period of the Civil War as well as an assortment of pamphlets, advertising materials, books, and music.
Contents List
- Correspondence, Abi - Gru (Box 1)
- Correspondence, Hal - Sla (Box 2)
- Correspondence, Sma - Vir (Box 3)
- Correspondence, W - Z, and Miscellaneous (Box 4)
- Index to Correspondence, Unnumbered items, typescript and manuscript (Box 5)
- General correspondence and book orders, Unnumbered items (Box 6)
- Tombstone Inscriptions Volume A, 1928-1941, 1 volume (306 pages, manuscript); 25 cm (Box 7)
- Tombstone Inscriptions Volume B, 1928-1931, 1 volume (284 pages, manuscript); 25 cm (Box 7)
- Tombstone Inscriptions Volume C, 1931-1946, 1 volume (308 pages, manuscript); 25 cm (Box 7)
- Tombstone Inscriptions Volume D, 1932-1941, 1 volume (292 pages, manuscript); 25 cm (Box 7)
- Index to Tombstone Inscriptions Volumes A to D, 5 pages, typescript (Box 7)
- Family Bible Records Book 1, 1928-1933, 1 volume (154 pages, manuscript); 36 cm (Box 8)
- Family Bible Records Book 2, 1933-1938, 1 volume (163 pages, manuscript); 36 cm (Box 8)
- Family Bible Records Book 3, 1943-1950, 1 volume (161 pages, manuscript); 36 cm (Box 8)
- Family Bible Records Book 4, 1934-1943, 1 volume (40 pages, manuscript); 36 cm (Box 8)
- Daily Journal of Anna Kagey Wayland, 1847-1865, 1 volume (212 leaves, typescript) (Box 8)
- Items from Anna K. Wayland Diary, 1866-1900, 1 volume (30 leaves, typescript) (Box 8)
- Militia Companies -- Heads of Families, Rockingham County, 1 volume (114 pages, transcript) (Box 9)
- Wartime Diary of Samuel Angus Firebaugh, 1862-1864, 1 volume (26 pages, typescript) (Box 9)
- Wartime Diary of John P. Louderback, 1862-1863, 1 volume (22 leaves, typescript) (Box 9)
- Wartime Diary of Joseph Franklin Kauufman, 1862, 1 volume (38 pages, typescript) (Box 9)
- Leaves and Branches from 300 Family Trees, 1 volume (420 pages, typescript) (Box 9)
- Shenandoah River Navigation, 1 volume (70 pages, typescript) (Box 10)
- List of Marriages (Shenandoah County, VA), 1 volume (158 pages, manuscript) (Box 10)
- Property Book for Rockingham Coounty, VA, 1798, 1 volume (158 pages, manuscript) (Box 10)
- Waterlick Baptist Church 1798, 1 volume (76 pages, typescript) (Box 10)
- Jefferson County (WV) Marriages, 1802-1884, 1 volume (150 pages, typescript) (Box 10)
- Five Courthouses of Rockingham County, VA, 1 volume (32 pages, typescript) (Box 10)
- A Virginia Commnity (Shenandoah County Survey), 1 volume (130 pages, manuscript) (Box 11)
- The Valley Turnpike, 1 volume (182 pages, manuscript, photocopy) (Box 11)
- 800 Colonial and Revolutionary Soldiers from Augusta, Frederick, Rockbridge, Rockingham, and Shenandoah Counties, 1 volume (207 pages, manuscript) (Box 11)
- Colonial Soldiers of Frederick County, VA, 1 volume (126 pages, manuscript, photocopy) (Box 11)
- Advertising Literature for Dr. Wayland's Publications:, 3 items, printed (Box 12)
- Wayland, John Walter.Battle of New Market. New Market, VA: Henkel Press, 1926, 24 pages, printed (Box 12)
- Wayland, John Walter. Bird's Eye View of the Shenandoah Valley with Map. Staunton, VA: McClure Co. Inc., 1924, 2 copies (Box 12)
- Song, "Old Virginia," from supplement to Normal School Bulletin Vol. 9, No. 6. Lyrics by John Walter Wayland, Music by Will H. Ruebush, October 1917, 2 pages, printed (Box 12)
- Wayland, John Walter. "Shenandoah Valley in History and Literature,"Normal Bulletin Vol. 7, No. 1. Harrisonburg, VA: State Normal School, January 1915, 24 pages, printed (Box 12)
- Wayland, John Walter. Sixty Errors Corrected: A Manual for Use in Public Schools. 2d edition. Harrisonburg, VA: 1931 (Box 12)
- Wayland, John Walter, "A True Gentleman," written for contest in the Baltimore Sun, 1909, 3 leaves, printed, photocopy (Box 12)
- Smith, Glenn Curtiss. Biographical Sketch. "John Walter Wayland: Veteran Historian of Virginia," printed in the Commonwealth, February, 1956, 1 page, printed (Box 12)
- Wayland, John Walter. List of Writings. (Box 12)
- News Articles, John Walter Wayland's Testimony before Senate Committee regarding Supreme Court, 2 leaves, printed (Box 12)
- Wayland, John Walter. Whispers of the Hills. New Market, VA: Henkel Press, 1928 (Box 12)
- Lucy Buck Diary, 1861-1865, 1 volume (240 leaves, typescript) (Box 12)